Guide to the Amsterdam News photograph archive, Series B-MT, 1920-2012.
Amsterdam News photograph archive
Division of Rare and Manuscript Collections, Cornell University Library
Amsterdam News photograph archive, 1920-2012.
8084
New York Amsterdam News.
189 cubic feet.
Correspondence, Photographs, Publications
Division of Rare and Manuscript Collections, Cornell University Library
Collection includes photographs and related materials covering a broad range of topics, with a particular focus on day-to-day life in New York's African-American community during the 20th century.
ORGANIZATIONAL HISTORY
Founded in 1909 by James H. Anderson, the New York Amsterdam News is one of the oldest African-American owned and run newspapers in the country. Initially focused on local news in New York in general and Harlem in particular, the Amsterdam News broadened its scope to include national news under the guidance of editor Dr. C.B. Powell in the 1930s. By the 1960s, the newspaper had become a major voice in the national African-American community, offering extensive coverage of the civil rights movement. Beginning in 1982, the newspaper was edited by Wilbert A. Tatum, under whose guidance the newspaper remained a voice in local and national affairs. In 1996, Tatum turned control of the newspaper over to his daughter, Elinor Tatum, who remained the publisher and editor-in-chief through the 2000s.
COLLECTION DESCRIPTION
Collection includes photographs and related materials covering a broad range of topics, with a particular focus on day-to-day life in New York's African-American community during the 20th century. Subjects include civil rights marches and protests, church events, high school graduations, local politics, and fashion. Some photographs were taken by staff photographers, while others originated with wire services or as submissions from individuals or agencies. Formats in the collection include silver gelatin prints, negatives (including many unpublished images), contact sheets, Polaroids, wire photos, and halftone prints. As the working photo archive of a continuously-published newspaper, many of the images have retouching, attached captions, press releases, cover letters, and printer's instructions. In addition to photographs, the collection includes ephemera and manuscript material, including newspaper article drafts, typescript and mimeographed speeches, correspondence, event programs, magazine and newspaper clippings, employment applications, press releases, and newspaper production materials.
The bulk of the materials in the archive range from the mid-1940s through the mid-1990s. The materials are divided into series, reflecting the organization of the materials in the AM News offices. A major sub-series of the collection is the archive of Mel Tapley, who began working for the Amsterdam News in 1942 and served as entertainment editor until his retirement in 1997. The Mel Tapley archive includes a wide variety of material, including correspondence, manuscript and typescript articles and notes, artwork, press kits, publicity photos, and printing plates for comic strips drawn by Tapley.
Photographers represented in the collection include Bert Andrews, Kwame Brathwaite, Al Burley, James C. Campbell, Curt Clemons, Juanita M. Cole, Karl Crutchfield, L. St. Clair Dummett, Monroe S. Frederick II, James Gilbert, Dave Greene, Austin Hansen, Tex Harris, Bob Head, Cecil Layne, David McAdams, Bill Moore, Allen Morgan, Vondel Nichols, Lem Peterkin, George M. West, and Lloyd Yearwood. Photo agencies and services represented include Pictorial Enterprise, Wide World Photo, Harris Photo, News Voice International, Rapid News Photo, United Press International, Negro Press Photo Service, Wagner International Photos, and Ace Creative Photos.
SUBJECTS
Names:
New York Amsterdam News.
Titles:
New York Amsterdam news.
Subjects:
African American newspapers.; African Americans -- New York (State) -- New York.
Places:
New York (N.Y.); Harlem (New York, N.Y.)
Form and Genre Terms:
Photographs.
INFORMATION FOR USERS
SERIES LIST
Because of the size of this collection, the guide is broken up into several different pages. Each page is then further separated into different series. The majority of the sereis titles come from titles given by the Amsterdam News.
Main Guide Content Listing
Series A. Main photo sequence
The main alphabetic sequence of prints containing material from 1920-2012 with the bulk being 1944-1996.
Subject files A
Subject files B
Subject files C
Subject files D
Subject files E
Subject files F
Subject files G
Subject files H
Subject files I
Subject files J
Subject files K
Subject files L
Subject files M
Subject files N
Subject files O
Subject files P
Subject files Q
Subject files R
Subject files S
Subject files T
Subject files U
Subject files V
Subject files W
Subject files X
Subject files Y
Subject files Z
Series B. Inactive File
File of inactive, defunct, or deceased individuals and organizations. Bulk material dates from before 1980.
Series C. Presorted Photos
A roughly sorted series of photos.
Series D. Semi Alphabetized Photos
A second roughly sorted series of photos. Most date from 1980-1999.
Series E. Dated Folders
Photos from the 1990s sorted by date.
Series F. Sports Photos
Mostly promotional photos from sports teams.
Series G. Contemporary File
An alphabetic sequence of photos primarily from 1988-2000, but with some older material.
Series H. Transfer File
An alphabetic sequence of topical files with bulk material dates from the 1960s-1970s.
Series I. Dead Photo File
Photos from the 2000s organized by date of their publication in the Amsterdam News.
Series J. Loose Unsorted Items
Unsorted items found in various locations around the Amsterdam News office.
Series MT. Mel Tapley Collection
The personal archive of Mel Tapley, who began working at the Amsterdam News in 1942 and served as the entertainment editor until 1997. Includes a wide variety of ephemera, artwork, manuscript and typescript material, and correspondence.
Miscellaneous Mailings and Press Files
Mel Tapley Artwork
Unsorted Photos
Press Mailings
Books and Booklets
Press Kits
Press Releases
Oversize and Fax Press Releases
Periodicals, Newspapers, Magazines
Audio and Visual Media
CONTAINER LIST
- Series B. Inactive File, Pre 1980
  File of inactive, defunct, or deceased individuals and organizations. Bulk material dates from before 1980.
  - Miscellaneous (Box B-1, Folder 1)
    Also one velox print, one image clipped from a magazine, and a typescript letter signed by Jon Lukomnik (Office of the Comptroller). One print has staple through border; two prints have staples through image area. One print is a Polaroid.
    Photographer if identified: Bill Moore, Duane Harris Photo, Coreen Simpson, Sally Mueller, Lem Peterkin, Daniel Dutka, Pictorial Enterprise, Robert Kalfus
    Number of Prints: 41
  - Miscellaneous (Box B-1, Folder 2)
    Four prints have staples through the border; one print has a staple through the corner of the image.
    Photographer if identified: Bert Andrews, Monroe S. Frederick II, Pictorial Enterprise, Juanita M. Cole, Steve Friedman, Shelley Brown
    Number of Prints: 42
  - Adams, Grantley (Sir) (Box B-1, Folder 3)
    Number of Prints: 1
  - Adams, J.M.G. "Tom" (Box B-1, Folder 4)
    Also one velox print.
    Number of Prints: 2
  - Adderley, Julian (Cannonball) (Box B-1, Folder 5)
    Also two velox prints and two newspaper clippings.
  - Aldrich, Ann (Box B-1, Folder 6)
  - Alexander, Raymond Pace (Judge) (Box B-1, Folder 7)
    Also one velox print. Note on folder: "see Inactive file"
    Photographer if identified: Sam Miller
  - Allen, James E. (Mr. and Mrs.) (Box B-1, Folder 8)
    Also one paper stereotype matrix. One print has a staple through the border.
    Photographer if identified: A. Hansen Studio, James Campbell, A. Watkins, Cecil Layne, Dummett, Smith, Claude Maloon, James C. Campbell, YMCA of Greater New York, Walter B. Baker, Woodard's Studio, King Photographers, Pictorial Enterprise, Harris Photo
    Number of Prints: 29
  - Anderson, Eddie "Rochester" (Box B-1, Folder 9)
    Also one two-leaf press release, one velox print, and three paper stereotype matrices. Two prints have staples through border.
    Photographer if identified: International News Photo, Keystone Pictures Inc., AAF Training Command
    Number of Prints: 9
  - Anderson, James (Pfc.) (Box B-1, Folder 10)
    Two press clippings. Note on folder: "Deceased Medal of Honor winner."
  - Armstrong, Louis (Box B-1, Folder 11)
    Also two velox prints, one single-leaf press release, and one partial handbill.
    Photographer if identified: Harris Photo, Wide World Photos, James Gilbert, Bill Carter, Ed Sullivan, Allan W. McMillan
    Number of Prints: 17
  - Armstrong, Lucille (Mrs.) (Box B-1, Folder 12)
    Also one velox print. Two prints attached together with paperclip. One print has a photocopy of a typed letter signed by Joseph F. Lisa attached with a paperclip.
    Photographer if identified: Gilbert Pictorial Enterprise, Bill Mark, Parks Administration Public Information Office
    Number of Prints: 14
  - Asburn, Benny (Box B-1, Folder 13)
    Photographer if identified: Norman Frederick, Cecil Layne, James Gilbert
    Number of Prints: 8
  - Baker, Bertram (Box B-1, Folder 14)
    Photographer if identified: Big M Photo Service
  - Baker, Corinne Statum (Box B-1, Folder 15)
    Photographer if identified: Lloyd Yearwood, BroDavid McAdams, Harris Photo, Gilbert Pictorial Enterprise, James Gilbert,
    Number of Prints: 20
  - Baker, Ella (Ms., In memorium) (Box B-1, Folder 16)
    One two-leaf press release and one single-leaf photocopied press clipping.
  - Baker, Josephine (Box B-1, Folder 17)
    Also three velox prints and twelve newspaper clippings (one with accompanying mailing envelope).
    Photographer if identified: Cecil Layne, Harris Photo, Bro. David McAdams, George West, Whitestone Photo, International News Photos, Alex Hamilton, M Associates, A. Hansen
    Number of Prints: 27
  - Baldwin, James (Box B-1, Folder 18)
    One velox print.
  - Ballad, Florence (Box B-1, Folder 19)
  - Banneker, Benjamin (Box B-1, Folder 20)
  - Barnes, Nathan (Box B-1, Folder 21)
    Photographer if identified: United Nations/Chen, James Gilbert, Yeshiva University Department of Public Relations
    Number of Prints: 6
  - Barnes, Nathan (Box B-1, Folder 22)
    One velox print, one funeral program, one four-leaf press release, one stamped funeral announcement with ms. additions, one photocopied c.v. (three leaves), and two newspaper clippings.
  - Basie, Catherine (Mrs.) (Box B-1, Folder 23)
    Photographer if identified: Reni Photos, Regency Pictorials Inc., Gill Photographers, Gilbert Pictorial Enterprise, Arthur J. Corr, Harris Photo, Cecil Layne, Frederick A. Schroeder, Schroeder & Corr, Ed Sullivan, Mrs. H. David Rogers.
    Number of Prints: 19
  - Basie, Count (Box B-1, Folder 24)
    Also one velox print. One bundle of four prints and one bundle of two prints stuck together with paste. One print has caption attached with staple through border.
    Photographer if identified: United Press International Inc., Mike Hall Assoc., Pictorial Enterprise, Juanita M. Cole, Z. A. Wiggins, Harris Photo
    Number of Prints: 28
  - Basie, Count (Box B-1, Folder 25)
    One bundle of two prints and one bundle of approximately 6 prints stuck together with paste. Two photos stapled together at border.
    Photographer if identified: Pictorial Enterprise, Bryan D. Hall, Channel 21, Monmouth County Arts Council, David Workman Photography, James C. Campbell, James Gilbert, Jay McShann, O'Brien, Harris Photo
    Number of Prints: 40
  - Bennett, Howard (Box B-1, Folder 26)
    Also one velox print, one newspaper clipping, and a single-leaf computer-printed typescript text entitled "Somewhere Dr. King is Smiling" by Stevie Wonder.
    Photographer if identified: Gilbert Pictorial Enterprise, Al Levine, James Campbell, Pictorial Enterprise, Harris Photo, Monroe S. Frederick II
    Number of Prints: 12
  - Bishop, Maurice (Box B-1, Folder 27)
    Also one velox print and one newspaper clipping.
    Photographer if identified: Frank Dexter
    Number of Prints: 5
  - Bishop, Maurice (Box B-1, Folder 28)
    Photographer if identified: Kwame Brathwaite
  - Blake, Eubie (Box B-1, Folder 29)
    Also three velox prints. Two prints are stuck together with paste; another two stuck together with tape.
    Photographer if identified: Dave Greene, Lem Peterkin's Photo, Coreen Simpson, Hy Zazula Associates, Amas Repert[ory Theatre] Inc., Norman Frederick, Ace Creative Photos, James Gilbert, Hamilton Associates, Mullam
    Number of Prints: 34
  - Bontemps, Arna (Box B-1, Folder 30)
    One newspaper clipping.
  - Bostic, Joe (Box B-1, Folder 31)
    Also two single-image negatives. One print is pasted onto a small piece of art board.
    Photographer if identified: Barry Kramer, Merritt Photo, Tex Harris, Herbert Hawkins
  - Bostic, Joseph E. (Box B-1, Folder 32)
  - Boxley, Calvin (Box B-1, Folder 33)
  - Boyd, LeRoy (Box B-1, Folder 34)
    Photographer if identified: James Gilbert
  - Boyland, Thomas S. (Box B-1, Folder 35)
    Also one newspaper clipping.
    Photographer if identified: Portfolio International Inc.
    Number of Prints: 3
  - Bradley, Omar N. (General) (Box B-1, Folder 36)
    One carbonscript news article and nine newspaper clippings.
  - Bramwell, Lula (Box B-1, Folder 37)
    3 typescript texts (totaling 8 leaves), one typed letter signed by Inez Smith Reid, and one single-leaf text removed from an unidentified source.
  - Bramwell, Lula (Box B-1, Folder 38)
    Photographer if identified: Harris Photo, Curt Clemons,
  - Brannic, LeRoy M. (Box B-1, Folder 39)
    Typescript obituary attached to print with paperclip.
    Photographer if identified: Gilbert Pictorial Enterprise
  - Brewer, Guy R. (Box B-1, Folder 40)
    One mimeographed press release, one two-leaf typescript meeting resolution (plus a carbonscript copy of the second leaf), one two-leaf typescript editorial (with attached ms. note and two-leaf carbonscript statement), one three-leaf typescript text of a speech given by Guy R. Brewer on Jan. 12, 1946, a two-leaf typescript article about the event at which that speech was given, one carbonscript editorial, one typed letter signed by Nevill B. Lake (one leaf, with accompanying envelope), one carbonscript legal summons (4 leaves total), and 6 newspaper clippings.
  - Brewer, Guy R. (Box B-1, Folder 41)
    Also three velox prints. One print has caption attached with staple through border.
    Photographer if identified: Paul Costin, Gill Photographers, Bill Hayes Photography, Dick De Marsico, Wilson, President Borough of Queens
    Number of Prints: 13
  - Bricktop (Box B-1, Folder 42)
    Also one velox print. Approximately 4 prints are stuck together with paste.
    Photographer if identified: David J. M. Robinson, Wagner International Photos Inc., John Whyte
  - Bronson, Samuel (Box B-1, Folder 43)
    Photographer if identified: Harris Photo
  - Brooks, Charlie (Jr.) (Box B-1, Folder 44)
    Two newspaper clippings.
  - Brooks, Ed (Box B-1, Folder 45)
  - Brown, Earl (Box B-1, Folder 46)
    One print has caption attached with staple through border.
    Photographer if identified: David McAdams, Hale Haberman, Rapid News Photo, James C. Campbell, Maurey Garber, Nichols, Dummett, Harold T. Cooper, Mallory Photo, A. Hansen Studio, Cecil Layne, News-Ad Photography
    Number of Prints: 31
  - Brown, Earl (clippings) (Box B-1, Folder 47)
    One typed letter signed by Earl Brown, one two-leaf typescript press release, one single-leaf typescript press release, one three-leaf typescript editorial with extensive ms. additions and corrections, one two-leaf typescript editorial, one typed letter signed by Earl [Brown], one three-leaf carbonscript editorial, one carbonscript newspaper article draft, three single-leaf carbonscript resolutions, one single-leaf carbonscript editorial, one two-leaf carbonscript editorial, one two-leaf press release, one single-leaf press release, one three-leaf typescript press release with ms. additions, one six-leaf carbonscript press release with ms. additions, one 10-leaf mimeographed memorandum, and approximately 36 newspaper clippings.
  - Brown, Earl (vs. Powell) (Box B-1, Folder 48)
    A two-leaf mimeographed press release, a four-leaf typescript press release, an Earl Brown canvassing flier, a two-leaf mimeographed press release, a four-leaf mimeographed press release, a four-leaf typescript editorial with extensive ms. additions, a two-leaf carbonscript letter from Earl Brown to Adam Clayton Powell, and approximately 28 newspaper clippings.
  - Bryant, Hazel J. (Box B-1, Folder 49)
    Number of Prints: 4
  - Bumpers, Elanore (Box B-1, Folder 50)
  - Bunche, Ralph (Box B-1, Folder 51)
    Photographer if identified: Wagner International Photos, Nichols, Cecil Layne, News Voice International, Photokraft
    Number of Prints: 15
  - Bunche, Ralph (monument) (Box B-1, Folder 52)
    Print is pasted to art board.
  - Bunche, Ralph (Box B-1, Folder 53)
    A three-leaf typescript curriculum vita, two leaves of ms. notes, a typescript letter (one leaf) accompanying a single-leaf photocopy of a typed letter signed by Edith M. Lerrigo and Helen Claytor of the YWCA, a ms. memorial poem by Howard Bennett, a mimeograph of a typed letter signed by Channing H. Tobias, a mimeographed of a typescript article with accompanying mailing envelope, two programs from Bunche's memorial service (both with extensive ms. notes), a two-leaf typescript "Bulletin," a three-leaf typescript newspaper article, a bundle of documents relating to the West Side Tennis Club (two press releases totaling 7 leaves, one single-leaf carbonscript editorial, one single-leaf typed letter signed by Emanuel Targum, and approximately 8 newspaper clippings), a two-leaf mimeographed press release, a single-leaf mimeograph issue of a telegram by Abe Stark, a single-leaf mimeographed press release, two mimeographed leaves containing texts by Lou LuTour, a two-leaf typescript news article by Harold L. Oram, a photocopy of a single-leaf typed letter signed by J. Bruce Llewellyn, two single-leaf typescript press releases, a single-leaf typescript biography of Bunche, the memorial pamphlet "Ralph Johnson Bunche: Peacemaker" (2 copies), a prospectus pamphlet for a Bunche memorial "Peace Form One: Dr. Ralph J. Bunche Memorial Project in the Arts," the periodical "Dateline" (vol. 1, no. 3, June 1949 - 2 copies), and approximately 73 original and two faxed newspaper clippings.
  - Burrell, Berkeley G. (Box B-1, Folder 54)
    Also one velox print and one two-leaf press release with ms. annotation. Note on folder: "See also National Business League."
    Photographer if identified: George West, Vernoll
  - C (misc.) (Box B-2, Folder 1)
    Two prints have staples through border, two have staples through corner of image. One publicity print of Earl Coleman is inscribed by Coleman to "Ed."
    Photographer if identified: Gill Photographers, Corporate Photographers Inc., Aristocrat Studio, Ted Sikorski, Pictorial Enterprise, LIU Brooklyn Campus/Sally Mueller, Von Thomas, Lem Peterkin Photo, James J. Kriegsmann,
  - C (misc.) (Box B-2, Folder 2)
    Also one velox print and one six-leaf packet of photocopied newspaper articles on Desiree Coleman. Four prints have staples through border, three have staples through image.
    Photographer if identified: Martha Swope, Juanita M. Cole, Paul Cox, Pictorial Enterprise, Shelley Brown, Bill Moore, Lou Manna Photography, Al Bunley
    Number of Prints: 38
  - C (misc.) (Box B-2, Folder 3)
    Also three press releases (4 leaves total) and one single-leaf artists' bio of Alfred C. Cobbs. Five prints have staples through border, one has staple through image.
    Photographer if identified: Pictorial Enterprise, Ruby Washington, Al Burley, Blakeslee-Lane, Allen Morgan Photo Service, David Gahr, Luigi, Chester Higgins Jr., Peterkin Photo, Raslavasky Photographics, A. Hansen, Marvin T. Jones, Shelley Brown, André Beckles, Poet-Eugene B. Redmond, Tommy Noonan, Cornell University/Charles Harrington
    Number of Prints: 56
  - Cade, Charles (Box B-2, Folder 4)
  - Caffey, Anita (Box B-2, Folder 5)
  - Cambridge, Godfrey (Box B-2, Folder 6)
    Also 4 velox prints.
    Photographer if identified: Metropolitan Photo Service, Wagner International Photos, Betty Lee Hunt, Paul Schumach
  - Camp, Byrne (Box B-2, Folder 7)
    Note on folder: "Deceased Jan. 1982, Funeral 1/19/82."
    Photographer if identified: A. Hansen Photography
  - Capers, William (Det.) (Box B-2, Folder 8)
  - Carter, Elmer (Box B-2, Folder 9)
    Two mimeographed press releases (totaling 5 leaves) and 3 newspaper clippings.
  - Carter, Elmer (Box B-2, Folder 10)
  - Carter, Lillian (Box B-2, Folder 11)
  - Carthan, Hattie (Box B-2, Folder 12)
    Photographer if identified: Michael Knight
  - Carver, George Washington (Box B-2, Folder 13)
    One mimeographed and one photocopied "Proclamation" (the former dated 1963, the latter 1967), one two-leaf "Thumbnail Biography]," one six-leaf (11-p.) mimeographed text speech entitled "Post-War Jobs for Farmers" by Clinton P. Anderson, one computer-printed typescript "Profile of George Washington Carver," one four-leaf press release, one newspaper clipping, one velox print, and one paper stereotype matrix.
  - Carver, George Washington (Box B-2, Folder 14)
    Also one press kit (consisting of a typed letter signed by Sean Callery, a three-leaf typescript press release and a three-leaf photocopy of the same, the pamphlet "From Orchids to Peanuts" by Robert and Leona Rienow, a typescript recipe for "Brussels Sprouts with Peanuts," and two photo prints [included in print count for this folder]); one four-leaf press release with ms. annotations, and one velox print.
  - Carver, George Washington (Memorial Institute) (Box B-2, Folder 15)
    Periodical Chemical Week (Sept. 13, 1952), offset-printed editorial feature "Introducing Slavery Into America"/"In This World: George Washington Carver" by Gretter Features, and two copies of a fund-raising form for a Carver memorial with accompanying typed letter signed by "Tex" Brady (1 leaf).
  - Cave, Herbert (Dr.) (Box B-2, Folder 16)
    Photographer if identified: Pictorial Enterprise, Bill Carter,
  - Chauncey, Harrell (Box B-2, Folder 17)
    Also typescript text of a funeral announcement (1 leaf), funeral program, two-leaf typescript notes for obituary, a three-leaf mimeographed press release (2 copies), three-leaf mimeographed text "L.S.D. - An Art Form," photocopied single-leaf typed letter signed by Sidney Shulman, mimeographed "Live Social Drama" handbill, one photocopied newspaper clipping, one photocopied program from the Excellence in Communications Awards, and 4 velox prints.
    Photographer if identified: Studio Twelve, Bob Head, Harris Photo
  - Chinn, May Edward (Box B-2, Folder 18)
  - Clark, James I. (Bishop) (Box B-2, Folder 19)
  - Clark, Mamie (Dr.) (Box B-2, Folder 20)
    Also four velox prints.
    Photographer if identified: Harris Photo, Norman Frederick, Gary Scott, James Gilbert, D'Arlene Studio, ABC Press Relations, Bradford Bachrach
  - Clark, Michele (Box B-2, Folder 21)
  - Clark, Odell (Box B-2, Folder 22)
    One print has a single-leaf carbonscript letter attached with a paperclip.
    Photographer if identified: James Gilbert, Harris Photo, George M. West
  - Clemente, Roberto (Box B-2, Folder 23)
    Photographer if identified: United Press International
  - Cole, Nat "King" (Box B-2, Folder 24)
    Also one velox print and four paper stereotype matrices. One print is pasted to a piece of art board.